מזל טוב, Mazel tov, today's דף daf is דף ס daf samech
60 and we pick up at the top of ס עמוד א,
samech amud aleph,
four lines down ולרבי יהודה. u'le'Rabbi Yehuda. So in the middle of
a debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose,
the reason we brought this in was a statement that if the
מזבח mizbe'ach was chipped, that you couldn't שחט shacht a קרבן, korban,
but the question is but if there's no מזבח הזהב mizbe'ach hazahav
you can do the קטרת. ketoret. And the answer is when it
comes to the blood issues that's different. The blood issues require the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, the burning of the incense does not, and we're going
to connect this to a similar statement that was made by רבא
Rava about a debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yose, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda as we see said that
at the time of שלמה Shlomo the מזבח mizbe'ach was not big
enough, even the מזבח mizbe'ach that they were building wasn't big enough
to do all the sacrifices, so they sanctified the ground, the floor
of the עזרה azara to bring the sacrifices on the floor of
the עזרה, azara, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says no the מזבח
mizbe'ach was big enough and so on. And that has to do
with how you think of its relative size compared to the copper
מזבח mizbe'ach that was in the time of the משכן. mishkan. So
what we're going to get to in a minute but just to
understand what the context of this is is that, you know, okay,
might be that you can burn the entrails, the אימורים emurim on
the floor, you know, that's where actually you need a lot of
space, right, is to burn the entrails. That's why we were talking
about the surface area of the top of the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, and there of course you got a lot of entrails
you need a lot of space, but the blood stuff, that required
a real מזבח mizbe'ach and that's okay. You don't need the same
amount of space. You do some blood you get out of the
way, you do some blood you get out of the way, you
don't need a certain amount, so the blood is going to always
be different, right. So the burning of the אימורים emurim doesn't need
a מזבח, mizbe'ach, the burning of the entrails we're now about to
see according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and presumably רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose does not argue in theory does not need the מזבח mizbe'ach
you could sanctify the floor. The focus of the מזבח mizbe'ach is
about the blood and that's where you need the מזבח mizbe'ach and
we'll get back to that in a minute. Within the middle of
that the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yose, so as we said it was sort of linked to the
relative size of the מזבח mizbe'ach of שלמה Shlomo to the מזבח
mizbe'ach of the time of משה. Moshe. And that's because based on
how they read the verses, although the verse says it was five
by five by three they each have a different way of reading
that verse. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reads it was actually 10 by
10, five by five measured from the center by three, which makes
it low and very wide, which shows why he thought that there
was a lot of space even by משה's Moshe altar, whereas רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose says it was five by five but by 10
high. Three was actually measured from the sort of the round about
sort of grillwork in the middle. Okay, so was narrow and tall.
That was רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. And that's where we left off.
Now according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose he's got a problem because
it says that the curtains around were only five, so that the
whole מזבח mizbe'ach was 10 and the כהן kohen then be on
top of that and be like so visible to everybody that's seen
as completely inappropriate. What are you putting curtains on if everything is
way visible. The whole sense of the privacy, the intimacy, it's not
just such a sort of so he had to say that no
when it says that the curtains were five it didn't mean five.
Since it compared the curtains around the courtyard to the אהל מועד
ohel moed and the אהל מועד's ohel moed own curtains were sort
of like 10 around its structure, these also were a minimum of
10 around its structure. So wait a minute if it's 10 around
the structure then what's the five? Oh, so it wasn't 10 around
the structure it was really
15. So the 10 means to the height of the altar the
same way the curtains of the משכן mishkan were 10 to the
height of its structure plus another five going beyond that. And that's
how come it allowed the כהן kohen to service in privacy. So
it's a rereading of two things: the מזבח mizbe'ach is higher and
the curtains are higher. Yes Charlie you had a question.
Yeah so they're talking about the the copper altar of משה, Moshe,
they're ignoring the משכן mishkan at שילה Shilo which had been.
Yeah, that's true but it's not relevant that is correct but it's
just not relevant for our purposes. But you're right. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara continues four lines from the top on ס עמוד
א: samech amud aleph: ולרבי יהודה הכא מיתחזי כהן. u'le'Rabbi Yehuda haka
mitchazi kohen. One minute, so now you explain for רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose by your reread of the verse that the curtains were five
אמות amot higher than the top of the altar. So fine, everything
gets done in privacy. But now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reads the
verse literally. Now the verse literally the curtains were five and the
מזבח mizbe'ach was three. Okay, but a person is generally assumed to
be about three אמות amot till their shoulders, which is like four
and a half feet. So if there
you are you're
three אמות amot and you're standing on the altar that's three אמות,
amot, so
your shoulders are six אמות amot off the ground and the curtains
are only like five אמות. amot. Okay, so you're also visible. Here
you are you're on the altar and the curtains, I mean they're
not whatever they're they're distant from you but they basically get up
to chest height. So somebody could see what you're doing or could
see you. And again that's not seen as appropriate and
privacy, the sanctity, part of that requires a sense of intimacy there.
with you with the עבודה, avodah, so that would be inappropriate, reading
the verses literally. So the גמרא Gemara says נהי דכהן מיתחזי, nihi
dikohan mit'chazi, it's true the כהן kohen was visible, but עבודה דבידו
לא מיתחזי, avoda d'beyado lo mit'chazi, you couldn't see what he was
doing, meaning, okay fine, you see his, you know, from his chest
up. But the עבודה avodah he's doing with his hands, and the
arranging of the, you know, limbs on the altar whatever, maybe you
get a sense he's doing something, but you don't actually see it.
So you don't see the actual עבודה avodah and therefore that is
considered to be appropriate. All right, so now it's very interesting like
to reflect about this and the idea of privacy and intimacy and
how you know you want that for the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
and so on. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא
לרבי יהודה היינו דכתיב. Bishlama l'Rabbi Yehuda hainu d'chtiv. Okay, so now
what fine, that explains how they understand the משכן Mishkan was arranged.
Now we're going to get back to what they did in the
time of שלמה. Shlomo. So it says the verse says if you
remember on that day ביום ההוא קידש המלך תוך החצר, bayom hahu
kidesh hamelech toch hachatzer, he sanctified the courtyard because the copper altar
was too small. Now the problem with this is is that we're
not talking about the copper altar. We're talking about right you've got
a new altar here. So there's going to be two ways to
read this. רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda way to read it is because
he sanctified the courtyard because the thing that was made to replace
the copper altar, meaning they're calling the new altar the copper altar
because it's the copper altar substitute. But what it basically means is
even the new altar was too small for all the sacrifices they
had to do that day, so they sanctified the floor. That's רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda read. So מזבח הנחושת mizbe'ach hanechoshet doesn't mean the
copper it means the new altar. Okay, then but according to רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi where רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi reads it what why
did they sanctify the courtyard? It should have said they sanctified the
new altar because the old altar was too small. So one of
those words have to shift whether you're based on רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi or רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So let's take a look. בשלמא
לרבי יהודה Bishlama l'Rabbi Yehuda according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that
even the that the new altar was was not big enough right
because it was not that much proportionally bigger than the one of
משה. Moshe.
So בשלמא לרבי יהודה היינו דכתיב קידש, Bishlama l'Rabbi Yehuda hainu d'chtiv
kidesh, he sanctified the actual courtyard because they had to use the
courtyard for all the sacrifices. אלא לרבי יוסי מאי קידש, Ela l'Rabbi
Yosi mai kidesh, what did it mean he sanctified the courtyard? They
weren't doing a courtyard, they were doing they were using the new
altar. So it says no, להעמיד בו מזבח. l'ha'amid bo mizbe'ach. It
means he sanctified the courtyard not to function as an altar, that's
a pretty radical read of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it means he
sanctified the courtyard so that they could use it for the new
altar. Okay, it's still not a little logical because whether big or
small or whatever, you need to put up a new altar and
you need to sanctify the courtyard. But according to רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi we're reading that day שלמה Shlomo sanctified the courtyard to be
a place for a new altar, and they needed a new altar
because the copper one was too small. Okay, but basically it's saying
they put up a new altar whereas according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda it's saying no they sanctified the actual courtyard itself to function
as an altar because the old one was too small. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like
this: בשלמא לרבי יוסי היינו דכתיב קטן, Bishlama l'Rabbi Yosi hainu d'chtiv
katan, that's why it says that the you know the old one
was too small but the new one will be the right will
be big enough even for the sacrifices they were doing that day.
אלא לרבי יהודה מאי קטן, Ela l'Rabbi Yehuda mai katan, but רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda what do you mean that the old one was
too small? Even the new one is too small. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says: הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, מזבח אבנים שעשה שלמה תחת
מזבח הנחושת קטן הוא. mizbe'ach avanim she'asa Shlomo tachat mizbe'ach hanechoshet katan
hu. The new altar that was that was the substitute for the
old one, even that was too small and they had to sanctify
the courtyard. Okay, so so basically based on רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
or רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you shift one of these words. For
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi you say it means they sanctified the courtyard
to put up a new altar because the old altar was too
small. And for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you said they sanctified the
courtyard to use the courtyard itself as an altar because even the
new altar which was substituting for the old one was too small.
All right, now finally to the reason we brought all this down
which was the difference between blood and other things. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: במאי פליגי? B'mai pligi? Oh I'm sorry, before
we get to the blood and other things, what is the debate
of how you read the idea that the copper altar of משה,
Moshe, the word רבוע, ravua, whether you read רבוע ravua to connect
it to the altar of יחזקאל Yechezkel to say it means five
by five measured from the center and it's going to be low
and wide like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, or whether you רבוע ravua
to link it to the gold altar of the incense and say
it's going to be narrow and tall like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi.
So what's that debate about? מר סבר דנים חוץ מחוץ ואין דנים
חוץ מפנים. Mar savar danim chutz michutz v'ein danim chutz mipnim. You
learn the outer altar from the outer altar. I'm going to connect
the altar of משה, Moshe, the copper altar, with the altar of
יחזקאל, Yechezkel, and the same way יחזקאל's Yechezkel altar רבוע ravua means
measured from the center, משה's Moshe רבוע ravua means measured from the
center. So it's not going to be five by five, it'll be
ten by ten in terms of length and width, low low and
wide. That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. ומר סבר v'mar savar
and you don't connect it to the inner altar, the gold altar.
ומר סבר v'mar savar and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi holds דנים כלי
מכלי. danim kli mikli. No, we'd rather connect two things which are
vessels because the copper altar of משה Moshe was movable right it
was part of the משכן. Mishkan. So we'd rather connect one vessel
to another. So if the רבוע ravua of the... the gold altar
meant the height was twice the width, that's what the רבוע *ravua*
of the copper altar means, and therefore it was tall and narrow,
and I'd rather make that comparison ואין דנים כלי מבנין *v'ein danim
kli mibinyan* rather than to connect the altar of משה Moshe *Moshe*
to the altar of יחזקאל *Yechezkel*, even though they're both outer altars,
but they're fundamentally different. One is a vessel and the other is
like a structure, okay? And therefore we're not going to therefore I
don't want to do that. Now, אמר Amar, רבא Rava *Amar Rava*,
so now that's the end of that's why I said that for
that's the end of figuring out their positions. Now we get this
idea that according to רב יהודה Reb Yehuda *Reb Yehuda*, they burnt
stuff, you know, they burnt the entrails on the floor, the floor
could function as an altar. So really? How far are you going
to take that? So אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava*, מודה רב יהודה
Reb Yehuda בדמים *Modeh Reb Yehuda b'damim*, that all might be that's
all very nice for burning the entrails. Burning the entrails you don't
need literally an altar itself, you just need something that has the
right sanctity, burning the קטורת ketoret, *ketoret*, the incense, you don't need
the inner altar, you can do it on the space of the
inner altar, but for the actual thing that makes it a valid
קרבן korban. *korban* for doing the blood work, that requires an altar.
That goes back to the point we said before: the blood is
always different. Okay, מודה רב יהודה Reb Yehuda בדמים *Modeh Reb Yehuda
b'damim*. Now what's the proof that the blood does require the actual
altar? דתניא De'tanya, *Detanya*, we learn a ברייתא braitah. *Braita*: רב יהודה
אומר *Reb Yehuda omer*, כוס אחד היה ממלא מדם התערובת *kos echad
hayah memaleh midam hata'arovet*. On פסח Pesach. *Pesach*, you might remember we
quoted this before, there were so many sacrifices they would be afraid
that somebody the blood of somebody's פסח Pesach. *Pesach* would get spilled,
they wouldn't know about it. So they took some of the blood
on the floor, okay, some and most of it had been caught
properly and this was just stuff that, you know, the קרבן korban
*korban* was done properly but you're not going to catch all the
blood. But maybe some of that blood was from a
קרבן korban *korban* that the blood had been caught but then the
כהן kohen. *kohen* tripped and it spilled and it fell, okay, and
therefore even though it was caught properly it never got thrown on
the altar. So you take from some of the mixture of the
blood, which is considered to have a little bit of all the
blood—we're going to assume that, I don't know why, you know, it's
a wide space, but okay, we're going to assume that's going to
have a little bit of every of all the blood that had
been spilled—so some of that might have blood that was caught in
a vessel and spilled and never thrown, and then you're going to
take that mixture and throw it on the altar, and then that
blood also will get to the altar. Okay, that's what he would
say you would do. כוס אחד היה ממלא מדם התערובת *kos echad
hayah memaleh midam hata'arovet*, they would mix up
one vessel, they would fill it up from the mixture of the
blood, ושופכו גבי מזבח mizbeach. *v'shofcho gabei mizbe'ach*, and they'd pour it
on the base of the altar. שאם נשפך דמו של אחד מהם
נמצא זה מכשירו *she'im nishpach damo shel echad meihem nimtza zeh machshiro*,
because if somebody's blood had spilled out of the vessel before it
got to the altar, this would validate it. So now we've got
a problem. ואי סלקא דעתך סבר רב יהודה כולה עזרה azara מקדשה
*v'ei salka daitach savar Reb Yehuda kula Azara mikdasha*, if the whole
עזרה azara, *Azara* had been sanctified to function as an altar, so
why do you have to do this? You had the blood in
the vessel, you tripped, it spilled on the floor, you just did
it. And this by the way works very well for the קרבן
פסח korban Pesach. *korban Pesach*. For something else you could say, "Well,
it's not two that's a four, it's not the wall of the
altar," but for the קרבן פסח korban Pesach, *korban Pesach*, remember you
only have to spill it, right? ודמם של זבחיך ישפך *v'damam של
זבחיך ישפך* (Speaker said 'v'damam shel'...), so you know, so it's so
therefore that's exactly what you did, you tripped and you spilled it
and it hit the floor, well if the floor counts as an
altar I just spilled it on the altar. Okay, so why isn't
that good? So you see that that does not work for the
blood. The floor has the sanctity of the altar doesn't work for
the blood. האי עבדיה למצותה *hai avdeih l'mitzvateih*, you just did it,
why should you do it again? So clearly it does not work
for the blood. So הגמרא *Hagemara* says no, that's not a proof.
ודילמא משום דקסבר שפיכה מכח אדם בעינן *v'dilma mishum דקסבר שפיכה מכח
אדם בעינן*. No, maybe the problem wasn't maybe it does function as
an altar, but you need to sort of use your energy to
spill it, okay, and it has to be human agency and not
that it just spilled out of the vessel. Okay, now by so
that's interesting, what counts as כח אדם *koach adam*, right? So you
know, an interesting question for example is when you're have to wash
your hands for נטילת ידים *netilat yadayim*, right? So do you need
a vessel? Do you need כח גברא *koach gavra*? The כח אדם
*koach adam*? If I open up a faucet and that allows pressure
to cause the water down and hit my hands, is that כח
אדם *koach adam* or not? Like when is it considered like my
energy, my power, my agency that spilled it? So here you could
say, "Look, even if I tripped, at the end of the day
my hands moved and the vessel turned over and that was like
כח אדם *koach adam*." Or do we say, "No, since that like
כח אדם *koach adam* includes the idea of intentionality," right? That's an
interesting question. Or even if it doesn't include the idea of intentionality,
if essentially I tripped and it spilled, okay, that would be like,
you know, that would be maybe like the floor pushed me conceptually,
right? Not like it was me, you know, my energy or something.
So this is a really fascinating question: what do you mean it's
not כח אדם *koach adam*? At the end of the day my
hand slipped and the blood fell out, so it came from the
energy that I provided if we're looking at it purely from a
perspective of physics, right? But no, somehow because it's not intentional energy,
even if you don't need it to be like an intentional act,
you need it to somehow be like directed energy, you know, to
be considered it was me who made it fall on the ground.
So therefore it says it could be the ground does have the
status of an altar but you... Know what, it's a different problem.
Spilling out of your hands is not the same thing as you
pouring it. You didn't pour it on the ground. Okay? And that's
why it wouldn't work. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, if that
was really the only problem, so why does he say gather up
the blood and go put it on the altar? אם כן ישקליה
וישפכיה אדוכתיה, im kein yishkaleh veyishpachleh aduchtei,
gather it up and then spill it back on the floor. Okay?
If the floor really has the sanctity, gather up the blood, why
do you have to go walk back to the altar? So that's
not a question already. So the גמרא Gemara, says ודילמא משום דבעינן
מצוה מן המובחר. vedilma mishum devainan mitzvah min hamuvchar. No, you want
to do it the right way. You know, why don't you say
every time, why do I bother walking to the altar according to
רבי יהודה? Rebbe Yehuda? I could just spill it right on the
floor. So of course you'd rather do it on the altar. So
the גמרא, Gemara, so it's not a total proof to רבא's position,
but yes, at the end of the day what רבא says makes
an enormous amount of sense because the entire מסכת masechet we've been
assuming obviously that you need a structure of a מזבח. mizbeach. It's
not just some abstract חידושא, chiddusha, you actually need an altar to
bring a קרבן. korban And if you take a look at תוספות,
Tosafos, right, תוספות Tosafos says, look at תוספות, Tosafos,
מודה רבי יהודה בדמים, modeh Rebbe Yehuda bidamim, very short תוספות. Tosafos.
תימא, teima, says the גמרא, Gemara מאי קסלקא דעתך מעיקרא, mai kasalka
daiteich me'ikara, how could I have had any possible thought that you
would not need an altar for the blood, which is funny because
the גמרא Gemara even tries to push back on the proof, but
תוספות Tosafos says it's impossible to imagine otherwise. והא קרן וארבוע ויסוד
בעינן, veha keren ve'arbuah veyesod bainan, we have all these discussions in
it, you need horn, you need it to be square, you need
a base, right? All those discussions. Right, remember the blood has to
be opposite the base. There's a, we've been very clear until this
point there's a lot of requirements of the actual structure of the
מזבח. mizbeach Okay? והן מעכבין, vehein me'akvin, and clearly those are, those
are absolutely necessary and required. Okay, so he's right, like it's pretty
obvious, but it's fascinating that the גמרא Gemara is willing to say,
you know what, fine, so it is obvious, you need the actual
altar for blood. But the חידוש chiddush is that you don't need
an altar for burning entrails and you don't need an altar for
burning incense. And again I go back to this theme that I
sort of said that I was sort of like was heightened for
me in this book I was reading, this academic book called "Blood
for Thought", which is how radically, right, the rabbis have like, you
know, emphasized the focus of the קרבן korban just on the blood
and on nothing else. Now to some degree that's like really reflecting
ויקרא Vayikra and the whole description there, although there it's not so
clear to the degree חז"ל Chazal read it that the עיקר ikkar
is the blood as opposed to the עיקר ikkar something else. But
if you read all of the story, stories of people bringing קרבנות,
korbanot, right, the emphasis is on what you're burning on the altar,
right? And you're burning the incense and it goes up to God,
לריח ניחוח, lerei'ach nicho'ach, and you're burning the entrails and it goes
up to God, לריח ניחוח. lerei'ach nicho'ach. So besides that חז"ל Chazal
already reread לריח ניחוח lerei'ach nicho'ach to de-anthropomorphize it and all of
that, okay, but the idea here that you have all these stories,
right, נח Noach built an altar and puts up a sacrifice, and
you know, everybody's building these altars. At the end of the day
the גמרא Gemara is saying, you know what, he could have actually
just burnt the entrails on the ground. All that stuff of burning
things and going up, that doesn't need an altar. The only thing
that needs an altar is for the throwing, is for the blood.
So it's completely consistent, right, with the idea that the blood is
the only thing that is מעכב. me'akev. But again, it just really,
you know, is a, it's a pretty radical statement when you think
about it.
You always said that blood is, with the atonement is through blood.
Right, so that is the one פסוק, pasuk, it's interesting, you read
all of the stories of, you know, of the what do you
call it, of people bringing קרבנות, korbanot, you do not, you know,
some of them don't even mention blood at all, right, think of
קין Kayin and הבל Hevel or whatever, right? It's all about putting
stuff on the altar and it burning up. Even if you read
through ויקרא, Vayikra, ויקרא Vayikra just goes through and it says, here's
what you do with the blood, here's what you do with the
entrails, here's what you do with this, it doesn't prioritize one over
the other. All of this assumption which is pretty much like the
entire מסכת masechet is really governed by like one פסוק pasuk where
the גמרא Gemara says like כי הדם הוא בנפש יכפר, ki hadam
hu banefesh yechaper, ואני נתתיו לכם על המזבח לכפר על נפשתיכם, va'ani
netativ lachem al hamizbeach lechaper al nafshoteichem, you know, לפני השם, lifnei
Hashem, כי הדם הוא בנפש יכפר. ki hadam hu banefesh yechaper. Now
even that could be it's part of the כפרה, kapara, doesn't have
to mean it is the sole thing, but it is that פסוק
pasuk that basically is what determines the entire read that it's all
about the blood. You're absolutely correct. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like
this. Okay, אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabi Elazar, מזבח שנפגם, mizbeach shenifgam,
back to the altar with a chip that we said. Now if
you שחט, shacht, not only if it has a chip is it
not an altar and you can't throw the blood on it, which
is maybe obvious, we also said that you can't שחט shacht because
it says וזבחת עליו. vezavachta alav. So if you שחט shachted the
קרבן korban and then fixed the altar, the קרבן korban is still
invalid because the שחיטה shechitah has to be while the קרבן korban,
is home, while the מזבח mizbeach is whole. Now, given everything we
just said, that's a focus on the blood, right? That's not true
like we said by the קטורת, maybe it's not true by the
entrails, you could burn the entrails on the ground according to רבי
יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda.
What about things that are not exactly about the blood, but are
maybe connected to the blood? For example, can you eat the meat
of a קרבן korban, if the מזבח mizbeiach is chipped? Okay, can
you, how about by a מנחה, mincha, right? What's the story? So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מזבח
שנפגם אין mizbeach shenifgam ein מזבח שנפגם אין אוכלים בגינו שירי מנחה.
Mizbeiach shenifgam ein ochlin bigino shi'arei mincha. You can't eat the remnant
of the מנחה mincha when it is chipped. Okay, so that's funny
because that's like out of the blood area, we would like maybe
more want to first initially talk about eating the meat, okay, but
the reason we're talking here about eating the מנחה mincha is because
that we've got a פסוק. pasuk. Okay, what's the פסוק? pasuk? שנאמר
ואכלו המצות אצל המזבח כי כן צויתי. Shene'emar ve'achlu hamatzot etzel hamizbeiach
ki chen tzuveiti. Right, this is משה talking to אהרן Aharon and
his kids about the מלואים milu'im and they say you're going to
bring this מנחה mincha and eat the remnant, right, in the presence
by the altar because that has how what I've been commanded. So
what do you mean by the altar? וכי אצל מזבח אכלו? Vechi
etzel mizbeiach achlu? Did they have to literally like be sitting right
next to the altar, standing, whatever, right next to the altar? You
know, they have the whole courtyard to eat it in. אלא, Ella,
the connection to the altar is telling you yes, the eating of
the מנחה mincha is conceptually connected to the altar, the same way
the שחיטה shechting of a קרבן Korban, is conceptually connected. אלא בזמן
שהוא שלם ולא בזמן שהוא חסר. Ella bizman shehu shaleim velo bizman
shehu chaser. It has to be whole and not lacking. And by
the way, the real thing we should have first talked about, which
is maybe the גמרא Gemara is now implicitly because if we went
this far, is what about the taking of the קומץ kometz of
the מנחה, mincha, which is parallel to the שחיטה. shechita. So if
the eating of the remnant of the מנחה mincha the מזבח mizbeiach,
has to be whole, presumably the taking of the handbreadth, which is
parallel to שחיטה shechita and leading up to putting the handbreadth on
the מזבח, mizbeiach, presumably that definitely has to be whole. So not
only is the blood connected to the מזבח, mizbeiach but by the
מנחה mincha or, you know, by the שחיטה shechita and the זריקה
zerika obviously, but by the מנחה mincha the parallel of the taking
of the handbreadth and the burning of it. And not only is
the stuff leading up to making it valid, but even the eating
that the כהנים kohanim do afterwards. Okay, and that's a real חידוש
chiddush because you would say once it's brought, it's brought, now let's
just eat it in the courtyard.
Now the גמרא Gemara is going to take that from the מנחה
mincha to the meat of a קרבן, Korban, right? So, which obviously
it makes more sense to say it by the meat of the
קרבן, Korban you know, certainly that's been our focus. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this,
okay, אשכחן שירי מנחה, Ashkachan shi'arei mincha, that's the remnant of the
מנחה. mincha. קדשי קדשים מנלן? Kodshei kodashim minalan? How do you know
it applies to like a חטאת chatas and an אשם asham that
that's eaten in the עזרה azara? but and that also has to
be eaten only with a whole when the מזבח mizbeiach, is whole?
תלמוד לומר כי קדש קדשים היא. Talmud lomar ki kodesh kodashim hi.
Okay, that's the end of the verse by the מנחה. mincha. It
is the holy of holies. So anything that is the holy of
holies is like this, can be eaten in the whole עזרה, azara,
doesn't even have to be standing by the מזבח, mizbeiach but it's
eaten in reference to the מזבח mizbeiach, or related to the מזבח,
mizbeiach and the מזבח mizbeiach, has to be whole. Now that's by
the way a powerful statement because
in general, how do we look at the eating of the כהנים
kohanim of the meat of the חטאת chatas and the אשם? asham?
We could just read it as like this is your gift, you're
the כהנים kohanim this is how you get supported, here's your opportunity
to eat meat. Okay, but a classic way the גמרא Gemara's reads
it, based again on a פסוק, pasuk, ואכלו אותם אשר כופר בהם,
Ve'achlu otam asher kuppar bahem, is כהנים אוכלים ובעלים מתכפרים. Kohanim ochlim
uba'alim mitkaprim. The כהנים kohanim eat and the owners achieve their atonement.
And that the eating of the כהנים, kohanim, like there's a phrase
משולחן גבוה קזכו. Mishulchan gavoah k'zachu.
Okay, but even משולחן גבוה קזכו mishulchan gavoah k'zachu is not exactly
the same. משולחן גבוה קזכו Mishulchan gavoah k'zachu means it's God's meat
and God is like giving you from God's meat. This meat belonged
on God's table, it was put up on the מזבח, mizbeiach. the
meat wasn't put up, but you know part of it was. And
God says it's okay, I'll take the fat, you take the meat,
welcome to my feast. Okay, it's going one step further to say
that actually their consumption is like the consumption of the מזבח. mizbeiach
Okay, and therefore that, you know, that as a concept, the כהנים's
kohanim eating is like the מזבח's mizbeiach eating. So that makes sense,
the מזבח mizbeiach has to be whole and therefore they have to
be whole. But I do want to point out an irony here,
which is are we still saying according to רב יהודה that you
could burn the entrails on the ground of the עזרה? azarah Because
if you could burn the entrails on the ground of the עזרה,
but the eating of the meat the מזבח mizbeiach has to be
whole, we're actually making the eating of the meat more connected to
the מזבח mizbeiach than the burning of the entrails. You guys with
me here? Right, we just said that for רב יהודה you don't
need an מזבח mizbeiach for the burning of the entrails. That could
be on the ground. But you need an מזבח mizbeiach for the
eating of the meat. That's a big surprise, right, that that is
considered more connected to the מזבח mizbeiach than the burning of the
entrails. Okay, now all of this makes sense by קדשי קדשים. kodshei
kodashim. By the way, the connection also of eating of the כהנים
kohanim eating and the entrails being burned or whatever we often know
from our famous, our favorite topic of פיגול. piggul. Right, that you
know intent of burning the entrails, intent of the eating and so
on. Anyway, but still here it seems if you're within רב יהודה
that the eating, as I said, is even more connected to the
מזבח mizbeiach. than the entrails. But now we're going to go to
קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. Now קדשים קלים kodshim kalim is eaten by
the owners, not by the כהנים, kohanim, not by people that directly
represent God, as it were, and not eaten only in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, eaten all in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So you would certainly
not for a moment think that that requires the presence of an
מזבח. mizbeiach If the, you know, you threw the blood, the sacrifice
was good, it got chipped afterwards, right? Here I am I'm at
home, you know, and I get a, I get a blood alert
on my, you know, on my iPhone that says, "the מזבח mizbe'ach.
was just chipped, stop eating your קדשים קלים," kodshim kalim, you know?
Like what! Like it's not, I'm home, I'm not even in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash anymore. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara going to
say, yeah, even the eating of קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim requires a
whole altar. So the burning of the incense and of the entrails
don't, but the eating of the meat of the קדשים קלים Kodashim
Kalim do. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: קדשים קלים
מנין, Kodashim Kalim minayin, how do you know קדשים קלים? Kodashim Kalim?
And it's assuming that it's true by that, and it just wants
to know what's the verse. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי Abaye
says,
אתיא מדרשה דרבי יוסי. asya midrashah d'Rabbi Yosi. We learn it from
the same place רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi learns this idea. And what's
רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yosi's דרשה? drashah? דתניא, we learned in a ברייתא.
רבי יוסי אומר ג' דברים משום ג' זקנים. Rabbi Yosi omer, gimel
devarim mishum gimel zekeinim. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said three things in
the name of three different elders. Meaning not each thing was in
the name of three elders, three things each one in the name
of a different elder. Okay, and וזה אחד מהן, v'zeh achad meihen,
and this is one of them. Okay, he said this in the
name of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. רבי ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Ishmael omer,
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael would say,
יכול יעלה אדם מעשר שני לירושלים ויאכלנו בזמן הזה. yakhol ya'aleh adam
Ma'aser Sheni l'Yerushalayim v'yokhlenu bazman hazeh. So assuming that the ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael has קדושה kedushah nowadays after the destruction of the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, that's a whole discussion, okay, whether it has the
קדושה kedushah for the aspects of the תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'ma'asros. Assuming
that it does, okay, what is the... so because of that, like
I have to, you know, in Israel... like in America, the one
thing you know is wherever you're traveling outside of Israel, just you
know, just give me the fruits and vegetables. Right, well, let's say
fruit, we won't worry about, we won't talk about bugs right now.
But whatever, give me the fruits and the non-leafy vegetables and you're
fine. In Israel, it's like oh my god, fruits and vegetables, do
I have to... what... did they take תרומות ומעשרות? trumos u'ma'asros? Or
whatever, fine. So that's what you have to worry about, and if
you say that the sanctity of the land for תרומות ומעשרות trumos
u'ma'asros is biblical, then it's you know that much weightier in terms
of כשרות kashrus issues. But he's not worried right now about a
כשרות kashrus issue. He's worried about what happens after you separate תרומות
ומעשרות. trumos u'ma'asros. Well, once the מעשר ראשון Ma'aser Rishon you give
to a לוי, Levi, but since you don't whatever, whatever, it's not
sanctified, anybody could eat it. מעשר עני Ma'aser Ani a poor person
you would give it to, but anybody could eat it. תרומה, Trumah,
כהנים kohanim can't eat it because they're טמא, tamei, so you have
to basically redeem whatever, redeem it and burn it or whatever the
case is by the תרומה. trumah. How about מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni,
right? How about the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni that you would do
on two out of every, you know, like on four out of
every seven years? You know, years one and two and then and
then four and five. What are you supposed to do with that?
Bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim and eat it. Well, it's sanctified. It's
not like מעשר עני Ma'aser Ani and מעשר ראשון Ma'aser Rishon that
is not sanctified. So, if I actually... or I misspoke, I'm going
to... go... I misspoke about redeeming. The redeeming was about the מעשר
שני, Ma'aser Sheni, not about the תרומה. trumah. The תרומה trumah actually
we take a little bit, I conflated. The תרומה trumah actually we
take a little bit and we burn it. I don't know if
you've ever, whatever, how you've ever done a הפרשת תרומות ומעשרות.
hafrashat trumos u'ma'asros. It's also fed to the animals in the zoo
that are owned by a כהן.
kohen Oh really? Fascinating. Anyway, because you don't... the animals don't have
to be טהור. tahor. Anyway, so I don't know if you've ever
done הפרשת... hafrashat... that's true... I don't know if you've ever done
a הפרשת תרומות ומעשרות. hafrashat trumos u'ma'asros. But anyway, so a little
bit of תרומה, trumah, like one little tiny thing is תרומה, trumah,
okay, and that you deal with, okay. The normal מעשר ma'aser is
not sanctified so you can eat it. What do you do with
the מעשר שני? Ma'aser Sheni? So the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni what
we do if you're מפריש mafirish it in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
is you basically say, okay, ten percent of this stuff is מעשר
שני Ma'aser Sheni and I'm going to redeem it all on a
פרוטה perutah worth of a particular coin that I have stored somewhere.
That's how you deal with it, okay, and then you're able to
eat it. But comes along רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael and רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Ishmael is saying like, wait, why don't why why you don't
have to do that and maybe you even shouldn't do that? Because
I get that you can't eat תרומה trumah nowadays, the כהן can't
because he's טמא, tamei, okay, but this stuff, okay, you don't have
to be טהור tahor to eat מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni. You know,
just go
do... לא אכלתי באוני ממנו ולא בערתי ממנו בטמא. lo akhalti v'oni
mimenu v'lo bi'arti mimenu b'tamei. No, actually you do, I take that
back. You have to be טהור? tahor? I guess he's... assumed yes.
I guess he's assuming you are טהור. tahor.
Alright, but it's not as
severe.
Right, right, right, right, right. Okay, so he's ignoring the טומאה-טהרה. tumah-taharah.
I'm trying to too much contemporary... make this relevant contemporary in a
contemporary way that I'm confusing everybody, myself included. Anyway, okay, fine. Forget
that. Let's assume you're טהור. tahor. Okay, but he is saying, anyway
he is saying, maybe you should be able to go ahead, bring
it to ירושלים Yerushalayim and eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Why not?
You know, you don't bring מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni to the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you just, you know, you just go ahead and
eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So if it has... if if the
stuff is... if תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros are biblical, the land has
sanctity nowadays for תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'ma'asros. So why do something like
redeem the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni or whatever you're going to do?
Okay, assuming you are טהור, tahor, just go ahead and bring it
and eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, so that's the question. רבי
ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Ishmael omer, יכול יעלה אדם מעשר שני לירושלים ויאכלנו
בזמן הזה. yakhol ya'aleh adam Ma'aser Sheni l'Yerushalayim v'yokhlenu bazman hazeh.
Maybe nowadays you should bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim and eat it.
ודינו. V'dino. And it and so it makes sense to say that
you cannot do this. Why does it make sense to say you
cannot do this, even though it presumably does not require a בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it just requires ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Here's why it doesn't
make sense. בכור טעון הבאת מקום ומעשר טעון הבאת מקום. Bekhor teun
ha'avat makom u'Ma'aser teun ha'avat makom. By both of them they're supposed
to be brought ירושלים. Yerushalayim. the בכור Bchor and the מעשר. Ma'aser.
מה בכור אינו אלא בפני הבית, Mah Bchor eino ela bifnei habayis,
the same way בכור Bchor is only in the presence of a
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because it's a קרבן, Korban. אף מעשר אינו
אלא בפני הבית. af Ma'aser eino ela bifnei habayis. So by analogy
to the בכור Bchor we should say no, you can't eat it
in ירושלים Yerushalayim nowadays, there's no בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So the
גמרא Gemara says wait, there's an obvious difference. One is a קרבן,
Korban, the other isn't. The whole strength of your question was that
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni isn't a קרבן Korban. and never gets brought
to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. מה לבכור שכן טעון מתן דמים
ואימורים לגבי מזבח. Mah l'Bchor shekein ta'un matan damim v'imurim legabei mizbe'ach.
Of course a בכור Bchor needs a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's
a קרבן. korban You gotta put the blood on the מזבח. mizbeach,
The strength of your question was maybe by מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni
you shouldn't require a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, ביכורים יוכיחו. Bikurim yochichu. No, but ביכורים Bikurim also is
not biblical, you don't do it nowadays. Why and why not? Because
guess what, you also need an altar. It says you bring it
to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you wave it and you
place it down in front of the altar, which is again what
the גמרא Gemara responds,
whatever he responds to himself. מה לביכורים שכן טעונים הנחה. Mah l'Bikurim
shekein te'unim hanacha. So no, it says והנחתו v'hinachto right לפני מזבח
ה' אלוקיך, lifnei mizbach Hashem Elokecha, place it in front of the
altar. So therefore, so therefore, we understand why those things
are require a altar, require, aren't done nowadays. They require an altar.
But logically מעשר, Ma'aser, which says bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim but
doesn't say bring it to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, maybe that
you're obligated and are able to bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim nowadays
and eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so the
verse says no, you
can't. והבאתם שמה עלותיכם וזבחיכם ואת מעשרותיכם ואת תרומת ידכם ובכורות בקרכם
וצאנכם ואכלתם שם לפני ה' אלוקיכם. v'havasem shama olosaychem v'zivchaychem v'eis masrosaychem
v'eis trumas yedchem u'vchoros bkarchem v'tzonchem v'achaltem sham lifnei Hashem Elokechem. So
it says you bring there all of your stuff, your מעשר, Ma'aser,
your בכור, Bchor, and you eat it there in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
the verse that speaks about bringing all this stuff to ירושלים Yerushalayim
packages together מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni with בכור. Bchor. So the same
way בכור, Bchor, although it is מקדש Mikdash focused בכור, Bchor, but
the same, but by being packaged together it's saying the same way
בכור Bchor requires a מקדש Mikdash even though that is a קרבן,
korban. מעשר Ma'aser also requires a מקדש Mikdash even though it's not
a קרבן. korban Okay? מקיש מעשר לבכור. Makish Ma'aser l'Bchor. So that
verse links them together even though you conceptually would have distinguished them.
And therefore based on that verse we say מה בכור אינו אלא
בפני הבית אף מעשר אינו אלא בפני הבית. mah Bchor eino ela
bifnei habayis af Ma'aser eino ela bifnei habayis. Yes, you don't bring
מעשר Ma'aser to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but it has to
be necessarily, it requires a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Without a בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash it's not eaten. By the way, part of this
question is how you understand the verse by מעשר, Ma'aser, because the
verse by מעשר Ma'aser is ואכלת לפני ה' אלוקיך v'achalta lifnei Hashem
Elokecha right מעשר דגנך תירושך ויצהרך. ma'aser degancha tiroshcha v'yitzharecha. Eat it
in the presence of God. So the presence of God is presumably
what we're saying. It might be it's sort of like the idea
that you need an altar to eat the meat even though you're
not doing anything on the altar. You need a בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash to eat מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. מעשר שני
Ma'aser Sheni is eaten in the presence of God means you're eating
it in a city where the central sort of focus of the
city is that there's a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So anywhere I'm
in the city is somewhat seen as right in the presence of
God. So that's what yes conceptually you don't bring it to the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but you need there to be a בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash for מעשר. Ma'aser. Very nice, makes a lot of
sense. Okay? So now we're going to continue figuring out like why
he made this דרשה drasha and then we're going to go back
to our larger point about the altar for the meat of קדשים
קלים. kodashim kalim. We're going to get back to that. But first
let's finish this in a minute.
So the גמרא Gemara. says now why did you need a פסוק
pasuk says the גמרא. Gemara ונהדר דינא וניתי במה הצד. v'nehader dina
v'neisi b'mah hatzad. Why couldn't you have just learned מעשר, Ma'aser, why
did you need a פסוק, pasuk, just learn it from the common
denominator of ביכורים Bikurim and בכור. Bchor. Okay? That both of those
need a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, the same would be true by
מעשר. Ma'aser. Don't say oh ביכורים Bikurim you place, because you don't
place בכור. Bchor. Don't say בכור Bchor you throw the blood because
you don't throw the blood of ביכורים. Bikurim. So the common denominator
is anything that needs ירושלים Yerushalayim needs a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Why do we need to learn it from the verse? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, משום דאיכא למפרך mishum d'ika l'mifrach the obvious
point is no, those two even though they're not the same, but
they share a very important common denominator. מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן
יש בהן צד מזבח. mah l'tzad hashaveh shebahen shekein yesh bahen tzad
mizbe'ach. Whether בכור Bchor or מעשר, Ma'aser, something you do, you do
some ritual with the altar. So obviously, not בכור Bchor מעשר, Ma'aser,
בכור Bchor and ביכורים. Bikurim. So obviously בכור Bchor and ביכורים Bikurim
can only be brought when there's a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And
there's no way to say oh if it's true about בכור Bchor
and ביכורים Bikurim it's true about מעשר. Ma'aser. בכור Bchor and ביכורים
Bikurim both have a ritual done with the in the by the
altar. מעשר Ma'aser logically you should say doesn't need a בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. And it's only because it's put in the package of
everything else that says bring it the בכור, Bchor, the מעשר, Ma'aser,
bring it and you know to ירושלים Yerushalayim and so on that
we say okay, even though it's not doesn't have a ritual in
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, מעשר Ma'aser also needs the presence of
a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And as I'm saying presumably that's the
idea of לפני ה'. lifnei Hashem. All right, got it? Now that's
the point of that דרשה. drasha. That's why you can't bring מעשר
Ma'aser nowadays. Okay, but it's not all that
convincing. Really? I think it's a pretty good פשט pshat of the
פסוק. pasuk. If it says bring all these things to this, you
know, you know, it says והבאתם שמה עולותיכם וזבחיכם ואת מעשרותיכם, v'havasem
shama olosaychem v'zivchaychem v'eis masrosaychem, it throws מעשר Ma'aser together with the
קרבנות. korbanos. It says bring these to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Presumably ירושלים Yerushalayim
gets its weight in that context from the presence of of the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
True, but the עזרה is still קדוש kadosh even today.
Well, that is an interesting question of does it need the structure
of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and we're going to get into
that. This is presumably
understanding that, you know, that it's a good question and that's why
there's this huge תוספות Tosfot or whatever which we'll get to in
a minute, but presumably, so you ask a very important question, which
is, if it is about that very logically you could distinguish and
essentially the גמרא Gemara, is going to get into this, but because
Charlie raised it we'll just say it right now, you could logically
distinguish and say, look, I get that מעשר ma'aser requires the sense
of לפני ה' אלוקיך lifnei Hashem Elokecha and requires that sense and
it is packaged together with קרבנות, korbanot, it needs there to be
that מקום המקדש. Makom HaMikdash. But maybe, and then this is a
debate in the גמרא, Gemara what would be if that מקום המקדש
Makom HaMikdash retained its קדושה kedusha and the sense of God's presence,
again there's a question of halakhic קדושה kedusha as opposed to the
metaphysical idea of God's presence, but for now let's somewhat see that
they're somewhat related, that idea of לפני ה' אלוקיך lifnei Hashem Elokecha
remains because the place retains its קדושה, kedusha, but you still can't
bring בכור bechor and ביכורים bikurim because that requires a physical מזבח,
mizbeach. which is just what we were talking about before. So logically
you could say, wait, I understand that if it lost its קדושה
kedusha I couldn't bring it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. If ירושלים Yerushalayim lost
its קדושה, kedusha, the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, the הר הבית Har
HaBayit lost its קדושה kedusha you couldn't do it, but maybe they're
packaged together because of the way they relate to the sanctity of
the place. But that's a different question than whether they relate to
the physical structure of the place, right? So that's an excellent point
that Charlie makes, which is exactly what the גמרא Gemara is going
to get into. But before we get to there, I just want
to point out, well you know, let's keep on going because from
this discussion we're going to get to this issue of can you
eat the meat of קדשים קלים kodashim kalim if you brought the
sacrifice properly and then the altar was damaged? That's going to be
the question we're going to get into. So let's take a look
because we haven't yet made that point. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, it's exactly going to touch on exactly Charlie's
point.
So מאי קסבר? mai kasavar? What does Rabbi Ishmael assume about the
sanctity of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Clearly or I should say specifically of מקום
המקדש. Makom HaMikdash. Clearly he assumes that the sanctity of ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael exists nowadays in terms of the agricultural aspects that מעשר
ma'aser is biblical or else the question would be moot.
Which itself is a מחלוקת. machloket.
Right, it's all a מחלוקת. machloket. Okay, but the sanctity of the
land of Israel for תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot is not the same
as the sanctity of מקום המקדש Makom HaMikdash to be treated as
still, you know, the sanctified מקום המקדש. Makom HaMikdash. Look, a simple
question is, can I go, if I go ahead and enter into
מקום המקדש Makom HaMikdash nowadays and I'm טמא, tamei, am I חייב
כרת? chayav karet? Right? To what degree does it retain the sanctity?
That is a different question from does the ground retain the sanctity
for תרומות ומעשרות? terumot u-ma'asrot? So clearly Rabbi Ishmael holds that the
ground retains the sanctity for תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u-ma'asrot. What does he
hold about the sanctity of מקום המקדש? Makom HaMikdash? מאי קסבר? mai
kasavar? What does he hold? אי קסבר קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה
לעתיד לבוא, ei kasavar kedusha rishona kidsah le-shatah ve-kidsah le-atid lavo, that
first sanctity at the time
of יהושע Yehoshua is for all future times. Now I just need
to pause for a moment. That's the classic phrase the גמרא Gemara
refers to is, was the first קדושה kedusha for all future times
or not? Here it's not really a question of the first versus
the second. It would be, I mean again there's a huge תוספות
Tosfot that discusses this, but it would be just as relevant for
the גמרא Gemara to say the second קדושה. kedusha. What it really
means is that the קדושה kedusha of מקום המקדש Makom HaMikdash is
retained even after the destruction of the temple. So right now our
question was not is that the קדושה kedusha of יהושע Yehoshua or
the קדושה kedusha of עזרא? Ezra? Like I don't care whether you're
talking about the first בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash or second. The question
is, is the קדושה kedusha of the place of the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash still present after חורבן הבית? Churban HaBayit? Okay? So don't
hyper-focus on the word ראשונה rishona right now. אי קסבר קדושה ראשונה
קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא, ei kasavar kedusha rishona kidsah le-shatah ve-kidsah
le-atid lavo, the sanctity of the מקדש Mikdash lasts for all times
even after the destruction,
so אפילו בכור נמי. afilu bechor nami. So why does he assume
you can't bring a בכור bechor nowadays? Okay? Meaning this question of
the need for a structure, the גמרא Gemara in מגילה Megilla says
that if the sanctity of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash remains even
today, then מקריבין אף על פי שאין בית. makrivin af al pi
she-ein bayit. You don't need the structure of a בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. You could just go to the right place and bring the
קרבנות. korbanot. People might know that every ערב פסח erev Pesach there's
a whole group of people that want to go up to הר
הבית Har HaBayit and bring the קרבן פסח. Ah, we don't have
a בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. The גמרא Gemara says מקריבין אף על
פי שאין בית. makrivin af al pi she-ein bayit. You can bring
a קרבן without a physical structure as long as the place has
its sanctity. Now as we just said, you need a מזבח. mizbeach.
So they said fine, we'll build a מזבח.
mizbeach If you have a קרבן פסח, they go on פסח.
Yes
you do need a מזבח mizbeach. for פסח. That was just the
discussion, you need to pour it, but you pour it on the
מזבח. Mizbeach That's just what, yeah, that's what we just said, that's
what we just said before. What?
They're saying they could use the...
No, that was exactly what he said. The reason you had to
gather the blood and throw it on the altar was you can't
use the floor for the blood.
The גמרא Gemara, was arguing in theory, but in the end that
was the conclusion. Okay. So if he holds that the place of
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash has the sanctity... Why are you assuming
you can't bring a בכור Bechor nowadays that you ask, oh, you
can't bring מעשר Ma'aser because you can't bring a בכור? Bechor? You
can bring a בכור, Bechor, just build a מזבח mizbeach, or something.
All right, so, איכא סבר קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא,
Ikka savar kedusha rishona kidesha l'sha'ata vekidesha l'atid lavo, אפילו בכור נמי,
afilu bechor nami, so go ahead and bring a בכור. Bechor. ואיכא
סבר לא קידשה לעתיד לבוא, Ve'ikka savar lo kidesha l'atid labo, if
you say that the place doesn't have its sanctity nowadays, so אפילו
בכור נמי תיבעי, afilu bechor nami tibei, so then ask what is
the story about בכור. Bechor. What do you mean ask what's the
story about בכור? Bechor? Meaning, if it doesn't have the sanctity, you
can't bring a בכור. Bechor. What does that mean? So, it's a
little vague what that means, but it's, but let's read it's clarified
at least the way רש״י Rashi reads it by what רבינא Ravina
says in the next line. So let's see what רבינא Ravina says.
אמר רבינא לעולם קסבר לא קידשה לעתיד לבוא. Amar Ravina le'olam kasavar
lo kidesha l'atid labo. Okay, it does not have קדושה, kedusha, the
place of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash nowadays. It does not have
the same קדושה kedusha and you cannot bring קרבנות korbanot nowadays. If
you were to go up there and put a מזבח, mizbeach you
cannot bring קרבנות, korbanot, okay? It does not have the sanctity. Okay,
and that's why, so what's the, so now, here's our question: והכא
במאי עסקינן, Vehacha bemai askinan, what are we talking about?
בבכור שנזרק דמו קודם חורבן הבית וחרב הבית. Bebechor shenizrak damo kodem
churban habayis vecharav habayis. You threw the blood, there you were, Nebuchadnezzar's
troops or whatever they were, Titus's troops were surrounding the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and you were saying just give me a second, I
gotta finish bringing my בכור, Bechor, okay? So there you were, you
were bringing your בכור Bechor and you threw the blood, okay? And
you, okay, well let's say this, the day before
they en, the the, there was the fighting was during the nine
days or whatever, on the eighth of אב, Av, you went ahead
and you brought your בכור Bechor whatever it was, the ninth of
אב Av in the morning, no, בכור Bechor is eaten for שני
ימים, shnei yamim, no, for, oh I forgot it was, for חמישה
שני ימים, chamisha shnei yamim, right? Okay, anyway, the בכור Bechor is
eaten for שני ימים, shnei yamim, right? נאכל לכהנים... נאכל בכל היום
ובכל הלילה שני ימים. Ne'echal lachohanim... ne'echal bechol hayom uvechol halaila shnei
yamim. Okay, so you brought your בכור Bechor on the eighth of
אב, Av, all right, there you were, you threw the blood on
the eighth of אב, Av, here you are you're home in your
house in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, Titus and his troops
are surrounding the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. This is the meat you've
got left to eat in your hiding place in some in some
cave somewhere, whatever you are in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And then they come
in on the ninth of אב Av and they destroy the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and they destroy the מזבח mizbeach and the whole
thing. And you want to know can you finish eating the meat
of your בכור? Bechor? On the ninth of אב, Av, let's say
the ninth of אב. Av. I know, it was near the evening
time. Okay, don't ruin my narrative. Anyway, so here's the question: הכא
במאי עסקינן בבכור שנזרק דמו קודם חורבן הבית. Hacha bemai askinan bebechor
shenizrak damo kodem churban habayis.
It's an interesting conceptual question. Okay, even though it's completely absurd historically.
בבכור שנזרק דמו קודם חורבן הבית, Bebechor shenizrak damo kodem churban habayis,
you threw the blood before it was destroyed. וחרב הבית. Vecharav habayis.
That was yesterday on the eighth of אב, Av, now ninth of
אב Av בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is destroyed. ועדיין בשרו קיים, Ve'adayin
besaro kayam,
and you want to know can I eat the meat? So here
what it's saying is that yes, obviously you need a מזבח mizbeach
or whatever, קדושת המקום, kedushas hamakom, you need all that stuff in
order to bring the קרבן. But what about eating the meat? This
is similar to the question of if the מזבח mizbeach? got damaged.
Can you continue eating the meat? Does that still need a מזבח?
mizbeach, Does that still
need a בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Does that still need that the
place retains its sanctity? What's the story with that meat? Okay? And
so, ועדיין בשרו קיים. ve'adayin besaro kayam. Now how do we, now
Rabbi Ishmael is assuming you can't eat that meat. How do we
know you can't eat that meat? ואיתקש
בשרו לדמו Ve'itkash besaro ledamo because what does it say by בכור?
Bechor? It says, you know,
we actually that was exactly that פסוק pasuk that was quoted. So
what was the פסוק? pasuk? ואת דמם תזרוק על המזבח ואת חלבם
תקטיר ובשרם
יהיה לך. Ve'es damam tizrok al hamizbeach ve'es chelbam taktir uvesaram yiheyeh
lach. It links the flesh to the entrails to the blood. They're
all linked by בכור. Bechor. So ואיתקש בשרו לדמו. ve'itkash besaro ledamo.
מה דם במזבח אף בשר במזבח. Ma dam bemizbeach af basar bemizbeach.
So that's, by the way, why we quoted this whole thing. The
same way the blood of a בכור Bechor needs a מזבח, mizbeach.
the eating of the flesh needs a מזבח. mizbeach, That gets back
to, so that's the point we were getting to all of this.
Because the blood and the flesh are linked. So if there's no
מזבח, mizbeach by קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, even though you eat it
outside of your outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, if the מזבח
mizbeach, got damaged, stop eating your meat of קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim.
That was our basic point. Okay, and again, ironically, possibly you could
go ahead and continue to burn the entrails. I don't know, but
anyway, but we won't worry about that right now, maybe maybe anyway.
But the meat, if you, if there's no מזבח, Mizbeach. you can't
eat the meat, even though you're not in the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, you're just somewhere in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Now, once that's true by
בכור, Bechor, now we know, oh, so not only the bringing of
בכור Bechor requires a מקדש, Mikdash, right? The actual
eating of the meat
requires a מקדש. Mikdash. So if that's true about בכור, Bechor, it's
also going to be true about מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Now again,
you would have said, not necessarily, maybe only by בכור Bechor since
it initially had to be on the מזבח. Mizbeach. Well, that's why
the פסוק Pasuk puts it together, because you're right, logically it wouldn't
have been the same thing. But at least now you understand sort
of the comparison. Okay. So it says like this: מה דם מן
המזבח אף בשר מן המזבח ואתי מעשר וילף מבכור. Ma dam min
hamizbeach af basar min hamizbeach ve'asi maaser veyalif mibechor. Okay, and now
מעשר Maaser you learn from בכור Bechor because they're linked together in
the פסוק Pasuk that the same way eating of the flesh of
the בכור, Bechor, not just bringing it, but eating of the flesh
of the meat requires an altar, so eating of the מעשר Maaser
requires an altar. But now, Charlie, it gets back implicitly and answers
your question because the גמרא, Gemara look, it's a very unclear... the
גמרא Gemara there's a lot of things to unpack. But the way
the גמרא Gemara seems to be saying it is that the reason
you don't eat מעשר שני Maaser Sheni nowadays is not just that
there's no structure, you know, it's also because it says there's no
קדושה Kedusha of מקום המקדש. Makom HaMikdash. Okay, and that gets to
your point. But the funny thing is, it's not clear how it
made that jump. Because the reason you don't eat the meat of
the בכור Bechor is because there's no structure, there's no מזבח. Mizbeach.
So why did we... why did we say that there's no קדושה
Kedusha to the place? We could have still said there's קדושה Kedusha
to the place, you can't eat the בכור Bechor because there's no
structure, but maybe you could still eat the מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni,
right? But anyway, so somehow the גמרא Gemara sort of glided, you
know, sort of glossed over that. Okay, but anyway, that's what we
are saying. So now the גמרא Gemara has its classic question: וכי
דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש? V'chi davar halamed behekesh chozer umelamed
behekesh? Okay, you know there are some things that are going to
get repeated. If somebody says, "What was your takeaway of learning in
מסכת זבחים Masechet Zvachim for four months?" and you'll say, "Here's my
takeaway: פיגול Pigul is a big problem and דבר הלמד בהיקש אינו
חוזר ומלמד בהיקש." davar halamed behekesh eino chozer umelamed behekesh. That's the
things I heard repeated the most. Okay, anyway. So בכור, Bechor, you
know you don't eat the meat of the
בכור Bechor because you don't throw the blood without a מזבח. Mizbeach,
And therefore you know you don't eat מעשר שני Maaser Sheni because
that's linked to the meat of a בכור. Bechor. But that's a
classic דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש, davar halamed behekesh chozer umelamed
behekesh, A to B, B to C. So the גמרא Gemara says
no: מעשר דגן חולין הוא. Maaser dagan chulin hu. מעשר, Maaser, even
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni which is sanctified, is חולין chulin relative to
קדשים. kodshim. And therefore these rules of these restrictions of making these
היקש היקש hekesh hekesh whatever doesn't apply to... doesn't apply to non-קדשים
kodshim issues. Okay, so that you're allowed to do a double link.
So the גמרא Gemara says: הניחא למאן דאמר בתר למד אזלינן. Hanicha
leman d'amar basar lamed azlinan. That's if you focus on the final
application. Since the final application is in קדשים, kodshim, you don't have
these
restrictions. אלא למאן דאמר בתר מלמד אזלינן, Ela leman d'amar basar melamed
azlinan, if you go by the source, the source is קדשים kodshim
and therefore you should have this restriction and you can't do a
double היקש. hekesh. So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי איכא למימר? Mai
ika lemimar? So the גמרא Gemara says: דם ובשר חד מילתא היא.
Dam uvasar chad milsa hi. It's not really a היקש. hekesh. The
meat and the blood of the קרבן are really seen as one
thing. That basically it's just more revealing to us. You know, the
blood requires a מזבח, Mizbeach, the meat requires a מזבח, Mizbeach it's
all one unit. And therefore it's not a double link, it's only
a single link from blood-meat unit to מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. So
now the גמרא Gemara, says like this: Okay, so that's basically what
we said and that teaches us because of this blood-meat link, that's
the reason we brought this in, that even if you threw the
blood, if you don't have a מזבח Mizbeach, you can't eat the
meat even by קדשים קלים. Kodshim Kalim. Okay, but we've also said
that the same way the meat of a בכור Bechor needs a
מזבח, Mizbeach. okay, and that makes sense because you have the blood
of the בכור, Bechor, but because the verse links them, the eating
of the מעשר שני Maaser Sheni also needs a מזבח. Mizbeach? The
important question that sort of was touched on here in the גמרא,
Gemara. not fully explored, was Charlie's question. Is the problem with מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni that it doesn't have the physical מזבח? Mizbeach. That
would have sufficed to be the problem by בכור. Bechor. That would
be ironic that by מעשר שני Maaser Sheni you could have קדושת
המקום. Kedushas HaMakom. Let's ask a simpler question, right? To really point
out the irony. You have a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, no חורבן
הבית, Churban HaBayit, and the altar got chipped. So you stop eating
the meat of the בכור. Bechor. That's what we just said. Do
you stop eating your מעשר שני? Maaser Sheni? Presumably not. Presumably if
there's a problem with מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, it is because of
the question of the sanctity of the place. So that's what remains
vague in the גמרא. Gemara Right? The גמרא Gemara spoke about the
קדושה, Kedusha, but then it also got back to the issue of
the מזבח. Mizbeach Which is it about? בכור, Bechor, it suffices that
the מזבח Mizbeach? is damaged. By מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, is that
linked so much that even a damaged מזבח? Or is that in
the end because of the question of the קדושה Kedusha of the
place? So now, let's continue. The גמרא says like this: Okay,
now כי סליק רבין אמרה לשמעתא קמיה דרבי ירמיה. Ki salik Ravin
amrah lishmaysa kamei d'Rabbi Yirmeya. When רבין Ravin went up to ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he said this discussion about the בכור Bechor and
the מעשר Maaser to רבי ירמיה. Rabbi Yirmeya. אמר, so רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmeya said a line that he's known for saying: בבלאי טפשאי,
Bavla'ei tipsha'ei, those stupid
Babylonians. דיתבי בארעא דחשוכא, Deyasvi be'ara dechashocha, because they dwell in such
a dark land, presumably it was very, you know, I guess it
wasn't right there on the Mediterranean, right there, you know, Mediterranean gets
a lot of nice Mediterranean sun, but also I think בבל Bavel
was very low, it's very dark, what? Yeah. Anyway, because they dwell
in a dark land, אמרי שמעתא דמחשכא, amri shemaysa demachshacha, they say,
you know, sort of dark, cloudy ideas. Okay. לא שמיע להו *lo
shemiya lehu* הא דתניא *ha d'tanya* בשעת סילוק מסעות *besha'at siluk masaot*
קדשים ניצולים *kodshim nitzolim* וזבים ומצורעים משתלחים *vezavim umetzoraim mishtalchim* חוץ ממחיצה
*chutz mimchitzah*. Okay, so here is a teaching that they could have
figured this whole thing out from. What's the teaching? It says, what
is the story, we're just reading this now in the פרשה *parsha*,
what is the story when the camp is moving and in transition?
Okay, is it still considered to be the camp? Sort of like
is that like the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* is destroyed? If you're
there chomping on your on your meat and the ענן *anan* starts
moving, and you've been eating your meat of your קדשי קדשים *kodshei
kodshim* or you've been eating your meat of your קדשים קלים *kodshei
kalim* and now everything starts moving, can you keep on eating your
meat? Are is it considered to be like you took the meat
outside of the camp, outside of הר הבית *Har Habayit*, outside of
ירושלים *Yerushalayim* because the camps have deconstructed or not? So let's see
what it says. Good question, right? בשעת סילוק מסעות *besha'at siluk masaot*
קדשים ניצולים *kodshim nitzolim*. You can't eat your קרבנות *korbanot*. But nevertheless
וזבים ומצורעים משתלחים *vezavim umetzoraim mishtalchim* חוץ למחיצה *chutz lemechitza*.
But the וזבים *zavim* and the מצורעים *metzoraim* can't be in the
camp. So what does that mean? It means that it's still considered
to be the camp. It's still considered like you have מחנה שכינה
*machaneh shechinah*, מחנה לויה *machaneh leviyah*, מחנה ישראל *machaneh yisrael*. The טמא
*tamei* people can't be in their respective camps. So here you have
everybody is like traveling, and if you sort of have like the
לויים *leviyim* here I'm not exactly sure what's considered, and you have
ראובן *Reuven* wherever you have, like the תורה *Torah* says ראובן *Reuven*
and the לויים *leviyim* and wherever you have, okay, so that's still
considered to be this is מחנה לויה *machaneh leviyah*, so זב *zav*
can't be
here in these other camps that's מחנה ישראל *machaneh yisrael*, so a
מצורע *metzora* can't be there. So even while they're moving it's still
the camp. So it's still like you have קדושת הר הבית *kedushat
Har Habayit*, wherever because that's still the camp still are there. קדושה
*kedusha* and קדושת *kedushat* קדושת המקדש *kedushat hamikdash*. Okay, but why can
you not eat your קרבנות *korbanot*? If the camp still exists, you
didn't take the meat out of the camp, just stick with the
right group and keep on eating your meat. So the reason is
because since the מזבח *mizbeach* is moving it's like the מזבח *mizbeach*
isn't present. It's a funny idea. The camp is present but the
structure isn't there. It's very similar to what we discussed before. You
have the קדושה *kedusha*, you have the camp, but you don't have
the structure. Okay, and therefore don't eat your קדשים *kodshim* because קדשים
*kodshim* as we said require a מזבח *mizbeach*. So therefore this is
like the מזבח *mizbeach* isn't present. It's not fixed, it's not put
down, it's not in the context of a structure. Alright, so this
gets back to the link not to the קדושה *kedusha* and the
camp but the link to the structure. ותניא אידך *vetanya idach* so
good. That says that you need a מזבח *mizbeach* for it to
eat the meat of the קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodshim*. ותניא אידך *vetanya
idach* but we've got another ברייתא *braita* that says בשני מקומות קדשים
נאכלין *beshnei mekomot kodshim ne'echalin*. That actually קדשים *kodshim* can be eaten
into places which we assume means when the camp is set and
when the camp is moving, that's what we assume it means. You
can eat the קדשים *kodshim* even when the camp is moving. How
do you reconcile this? Do you need the מזבח *mizbeach* or not
need the מזבח *mizbeach*? מאי לאו הא בקדשי קדשים הא בקדשי קלים
*mai lav hai bekodshei kodshim hai bekodshei kalim*. So he actually rejects
the argument and I actually logically this makes more sense. קדשים קלים
*kodshei kalim* do not require a מזבח *mizbeach*. Okay, קדשי קדשים *kodshei
kodshim* which is eaten in the עזרה *azarah* in the context of
the מזבח *mizbeach* only by the כהנים *kohanim*, that requires a מזבח
*mizbeach* and that becomes invalid when the camp moves because then you
don't have the structure of the מזבח *mizbeach* like in its place.
But you can go on keep on if you're here in
מחנה ראובן *machaneh Reuven*, and you got your קדשים קלים *kodshei kalim*
you can keep on chomping it as you're moving because that's like
eating the meat in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, eating מעשר שני *ma'aser sheni* in
ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, right, that does not require a מזבח *mizbeach*. It might
require the קדושה *kedusha* of מחנה שכינה *machaneh shechinah* but it does
not require that's not in relative to the מזבח *mizbeach* and that
you can even if the מזבח *mizbeach* is damaged even if the
מזבח *mizbeach* is moving. Yes.
And as a practical matter that would make a lot of sense
because if the כהנים *kohanim* are eating their קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodshim*
in the עזרה *azarah* they're going to know when the מזבח *mizbeach*
gets shipped but you've got to tell hundreds of thousands of people
stop eating, stop!
Right, right, right. It's like an עירוב *eruv* alert. Exactly. So the
גמרא *Gemara* okay so anyway so we'll pick up with this tomorrow
but here's a really fascinating question, A there's a question about מעשר
שני *ma'aser sheni* and to what degree is מעשר שני *ma'aser sheni*
connected to קדושת הר הבית *kedushat Har Habayit* and is it connected
to the structure of the altar? Right, but then there's another question
even by בכור *bechor* or קדשי קלים *kodshei kalim*. קדשי קדשים *kodshei
kodshim* is connected to the altar, but the stuff that you eat
in all of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, yes the blood had to go on
the altar but when you get to eating the meat how much
is that connected to the מזבח *mizbeach* or not? And here we
have two opinions. We have רבינא *Ravina* that says it's not, a
רב ירמיה *Rav Yirmiyah* says it's not connected and you can keep
on eating the meat and in בבל *Bavel* אביי *Abaye* etc. said
that it is connected and that you can't. And in בבל *Bavel*,
אביי *Abaye* etcetera said that it is connected, and that you cannot
go on eating the meat. And we'll pick up with this גמרא
*Gemara*. איכא דאמרי
*Ika d'amri*, there is another version. אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Papa*,
in a case where the מזבח *Mizbeach* was destroyed, everyone agrees that
you cannot eat the meat because the ability to eat the meat
is dependent on the existence of the מזבח *Mizbeach*. Where do they
argue? They argue in a case where the blood was spilled. In
בבל *Bavel*, they say that you cannot eat the meat, and in
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, they say you can eat the meat. What
is the logic of those in בבל *Bavel*? They hold that the
eating of the meat is dependent on the blood being sprinkled on
the מזבח *Mizbeach*. If the blood was never sprinkled, the meat is
not permitted. But those in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* hold that the
eating of the meat is not dependent on the sprinkling of the
blood. Once the animal has been slaughtered properly, the meat is permitted
even if the blood was never sprinkled. This is the second version
of the dispute between the scholars of בבל *Bavel* and the scholars
of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*.